{"tossups": [{"question": "After they were slow in pledging their allegiance to this king, the MacDonald Clan were massacred in Glencoe. Upon taking the throne, this king was read the Declaration of Right by Parliament; that later became part of the English Bill of Rights. This King\u2019s forces defeated James II\u2019s Jacobite uprising at the Battle of the Boyne, after which this Dutch stadtholder assumed power in the Glorious Revolution. For ten points, name this husband of Mary II, a Prince of Orange and 17th century king of England.", "answer": "<b> William III</b> of England (or<b> William of Orange</b>, prompt on William)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A precursor to this law known as the 15 Passenger Bill was resolved by Richard Angell after it was struck down by Rutherford Hayes. The Magnuson Act repealed this law, which negated immigration provisions in the Burlingame Treaty. \u201cYellow Peril\u201d motivated this legislation, which was passed after increasing immigration of an ethnic group following the 1849 California Gold Rush. For ten points, name this 1882 law that banned citizens from an Asian country from entering the US.", "answer": "<b> Chinese Exclusion</b> Act of 1882", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In 1925, this leader put down Sheikh Said\u2019s Islamist Kurdish revolt. This leader hired John Dewey to increase literacy rates by latinizing his country\u2019s alphabet. This man led a national movement that rejected the Treaty of Sevres\u2019 harsh borders and negotiated the Treaty of Lausanne. The \u201cSix Arrows\u201dideology of secular, democratic reform was developed to replace Ottoman norms by, for ten points, what modernizing first President of Turkey?", "answer": "Mustafa<b> Kemal Ataturk</b> (accept either underlined name)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This specific activity was conceived by Benton MacKaye, who opened its first section from Bear Mountain in 1923. A challenging section of this activity is known as the Hundred-Mile Wilderness. Randall Lee Smith murdered two women performing this action in 1981, and Mark Sanford used this activity to cover up his extramarital affair in 2009. For ten points, name this activity whose complete version can be conducted from Mount Katahdin in Maine to Springer Mountain in Georgia.", "answer": "<b> hiking</b> the<b> Appalachian Trail</b> (accept equivalents for hiking, such as<b> walking</b> the <b>Appalachian Trail</b>; prompt on \u201chiking\u201d and other partial, descriptive answers) Page 2", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This band, whose members included Roger Taylor and John Deacon, negotiated with the East German government to use footage from<em> Metropolis</em> in the music video for \u201cRadio Ga Ga.\u201d Another song by this band includes the repeated cry \u201cBismillah!\u201d and opens by asking \u201cIs this the real life? Is this just fantasy?\u201d In 1991, this band\u2019s lead singer died 24 hours after announcing his battle with AIDS. For ten points, name this British rock band fronted by Freddie Mercury whose hits included \u201cBohemian Rhapsody\u201d and \u201cWe Are the Champions.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Queen</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The perpetrator of this event was severely beaten by John Geary and James Parker, before its victim said \u201cGo easy on him, boys.\u201d George Cortelyou was unable to prevent this event, which took place at the Temple of Music during the Pan-American Exposition. The perpetrator of this crime was radicalized after hearing Emma Goldman deliver a speech on violence, and used a handkerchief to conceal his revolver. For ten points, name this 1901 crime that elevated Teddy Roosevelt to the presidency.", "answer": "<b> assassination</b> (or<b> murder</b>,<b> shooting</b>, etc.) of William<b> McKinley</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "These devices, including some installed on Arizona\u2019s Mount Bigelow, were improved after Cold War work on monitoring Soviet satellites inspired the development of adaptive optics. Karl Jansky names a series of 27 of these devices in New Mexico that form a Very Large Array. Isaac Newton invented a form of these devices with reduced aberration; that reflecting type improved on the refracting version, which Galileo used to observe the moons of Jupiter. For ten points, name these astronomical devices.", "answer": "<b> telescope</b>s", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {}, {"question": "During the third day of this event, James Stockdale commanded a squadron of F-8 fighters, claiming to have \u201cthe best seat in the house\u201d for it. The first day of this event involved a DESOTO intelligence mission that was tracked by patrol boats, after which the<em> Turner Joy</em> joined for support. After this incident involving the<em> USS Maddox</em>, Congress passed a resolution giving President Lyndon Johnson sweeping war powers. For ten points, name this 1964 naval confrontation off the coast of Vietnam.", "answer": "Gulf of<b> Tonkin</b> Incident (accept USS<b> Maddox</b> Incident before \u201cUSS Maddox\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This composer reused a theme from his<em> Gegenliebe</em> in a piece that had to be restarted at its premiere concert, his<em> Choral Fantasy</em>. That concert of this man\u2019s works also featured a five-movement symphony depicting a thunderstorm and a piece whose opening motif was used by the Allies to represent \u201cV for Victory\u201d in World War II. The notes G-G-G-E form the \u201cfate knocking on the door\u201d motif in, for ten points, what German composer\u2019s fifth of nine symphonies?", "answer": "Ludwig van<b> Beethoven</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "These units fought with allied cavalry that were organized into<em> alae</em>. These army units were divided into smaller units called maniples and organized into three layers based on experience. After twenty five years of service in one of these units, a veteran was granted citizenship. Each possessed an eagle standard and they were organized into ten separate cohorts, each commanded by a centurion. Thousands of men fought in, for ten points, what largest unit of the Roman army?", "answer": "<b> legion</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>John Bowring signed a treaty with this kingdom to grant Britain most favored nation status. Taksin the Great liberated this nation, which was modernized during the Chakri dynasty by (+) Mongkut. While it was ruled by King Narai of the Ayutthaya Dynasty, the Taungoo Dynasty of Burma invaded this nation, though this Southeast Asian country was (*) </b> never colonized by European powers. Several kings named Rama have ruled, for ten points, what country that was once known as Siam and whose capital is Bangkok?", "answer": "<b> Thailand</b> (accept<b> Siam</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>Aboriginal leader William Cooper led a march in Melbourne protesting this event, one of the few global protests against it. This event followed the announcement that \u201cspontaneous\u201ddemonstrations would not be hampered, made by Joseph (+) Goebbels. Over ten thousand men were taken to Dachau concentration camp after this event, which was a reaction to the death of (*)</b> diplomat Ernst von Rath. For ten points, name this 1938 event in Nazi Germany in which thousands of Jewish businesses and synagogues were destroyed.", "answer": "<b> Kristallnacht</b> (accept<b> Night of Broken Glass</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This man was advised by the half-French Poker Joe, and despite being previously absent, he led forces to victory at the Battle of White Bird Canyon. After having led his forces hundreds of miles from his native Wallowa Valley, this leader was finally defeated by (+) Oliver Howard at the Battle of Bear Paw. After this man\u2019s 1877 surrender to Nelson Miles, he declared \u201cFrom where the (*)</b> sun now stands, I will fight no more forever.\u201d For ten points, name this Nez Perce chief who fiercely resisted attempts at relocation.", "answer": "Chief<b> Joseph</b> (accept Young<b> Joseph</b> or<b> Hin-mah-too-yah-lat-kekt</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>A lecture by this author subtitled \u201cThe Monsters and the Critics\u201d argued that</b><em><b> Beowulf </b></em><b>should be studied as a poem, not as a pseudo-historical work. C.S. Lewis and this writer</b> <b>were leading members of the (+)</b> <b>Inklings, an Oxford literary group. A set of three jewels</b> <b>that are infused with the essence of two trees provide the title of a book by this man that was compiled by his son (*) </b> Christopher,<em> The Silmarillion</em>. For ten points, name this author who created Middle Earth in his<em> Lord of the Rings</em> trilogy.", "answer": "J.R.R.<b> Tolkien</b> (or John Ronald Reuel<b> Tolkien</b>)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "<b>During this conflict, a navy delayed their retreat because of a lunar eclipse; that decision by Nicias doomed the entire force. After Callicratidas lost at this war\u2019s Battle of Arginusae</b> <b>[ar-jin-oo-say], (+)</b> <b>Lysander retook command and won at Aegospotami. Alcibiades [al-</b> <b>si-BYE-uh-dees] defected from one side in this war shortly before the disastrous Sicilian Expedition, then later re-defected to (*) </b> Athens. Thucydides wrote a<em> History</em> of, for ten points, what 5th century BC war that Athens lost to Sparta, named for a Greek peninsula?", "answer": "<b> Peloponnesian</b> War (accept<b> Sicilian Expedition</b> until \u201cCallicratidas\u201d is read, then prompt on it until it is read) Page 9", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}